<topic>
	<head>
		<title>Nested Loops</title>
		<keywords>
			<keyword term="execution plan, nested loops"/>
			<keyword term="physical operators, nested loops"/>
		</keywords>
		<links>
			<link href="Execution Plan Reference.html">Execution Plan Reference</link>
		</links>
	</head>
	<body>
		<summary>
			<p>
				The <b>Nested Loops</b> operator performs the cross join, inner join, left outer join, left semi join, and left anti semi
				join logical operations.
			</p>
			<p>
				Nested loops joins perform a search on the inner table for each row of the outer table.
			</p>
			<p>
				Any rows that satisfy the (optional) predicate in the <c>Predicate</c> property are returned as applicable, based on the
				logical operation being performed.
			</p>
			<p>
				<b>Nested Loops</b> is a physical operator.
			</p>
		</summary>

		<section title="Properties">
			<table>
				<tr>
					<th>Property Name</th>
					<th>Description</th>
				</tr>
				<tr>
					<td>Logical Operator</td>
					<td>
						Specfies whether the <b>Nested Loops</b> operators performs an inner join, left outer join, left semi join, or left anti semi
						join logical operation.
					</td>
				</tr>
				<tr>
					<td>Predicate</td>
					<td>
						Specifies the join predicate.
					</td>
				</tr>
				<tr>
					<td>Outer References</td>
					<td>
						Specifies which values from the outer input are to be passed to the inner input as parameters.
					</td>
				</tr>
				<tr>
					<td>Probe Column</td>
					<td>
						Indicates whether the outer input is actually to be joined with the inner input. If this property is set, the join is not
						actually performed. Instead, all rows from the outer input are returned and the probe column is set to a <c>BOOLEAN</c>
						value indicating whether it had matches with the inner input. For example, using an <c>EXISTS</c> predicate directly in the
						select list of a <c>SELECT</c> statement causes this property to be set.
					</td>
				</tr>
				<tr>
					<td>Passthru</td>
					<td>
						Specifies a predicate that, if evaluted to <c>TRUE</c>, does not perform the join operation. In this case, the
						<b>Nested Loop</b> operator just passes the outer row without reading any row from the inner input. The columns
						from the inner side are padded with <c>NULL</c> values.
					</td>
				</tr>
				<tr>
					<td>Warning</td>
					<td>
						If present, contains a warning such as an absence of the join predicate and outer reference. In this case it is
						likely that a cross join is created accidentally.
					</td>
				</tr>
			</table>
		</section>
	</body>
</topic>
