<topic>
	<head>
		<title>DataContext Class</title>
		<toc index="3" />
		<links>
			<link href="Overview.html">Overview</link>
		</links>
	</head>
	<body>
		<summary>
			<p>
				The <see cref="T:NQuery.DataContext">DataContext</see> class represents something like a scope in which queries and
				expressions are evaluated.
			</p>
		</summary>

		<section title="Sharing">
			<p>
				The <see cref="T:NQuery.DataContext">DataContext</see> can be shared across multiple different queries and expressions.
			</p>
		</section>

		<section title="Link to Metadata Context">
			<p>
				Each <see cref="T:NQuery.DataContext">DataContext</see> is linked to a <see cref="T:NQuery.MetadataContext">MetadataContext</see>,
				which provides needed meta information, e.g. how to compare certain types or what properties and methods a type has.
			</p>
			<p>
				See <a href="MetadataContext.html">MetadataContext</a> for details.
			</p>
		</section>

		<section title="Elements in a Data Context">
			<p>
				A <see cref="T:NQuery.DataContext">DataContext</see> may contain different items. The following table lists all of them.
			</p>

			<table>
				<tr>
					<th>Element</th>
					<th>Description</th>
				</tr>
				<tr>
					<td>Aggregate</td>
					<td>
						An aggregate is a function that can be used in a query to perform aggregations. See
						<a href="/Extensibility/CustomAggregates.html">Custom Aggregates</a> for details how create new functions.
					</td>
				</tr>
				<tr>
					<td>Constant</td>
					<td>
						A constant is named value whose value cannot change. In contrast to <a href="Parameters.html">Parameters</a>
						this means that you cannot change its value. If want to change a constant you have to remove it from the data context
						an re-create it with a different value. The upside is that constants can be used to optimize queries and expressions
						by the compiler.
					</td>
				</tr>
				<tr>
					<td>Function</td>
					<td>
						A function is used to perform calculations inside of queries and expressions. See
						<a href="/Extensibility/CustomFunctions.html">Custom Functions</a> for details how to create new functions.
					</td>
				</tr>
				<tr>
					<td>Table</td>
					<td>
						A table is data source from which a query can select data. See
						<a href="/Extensibility/CustomTables.html">Custom Tables</a> for details how to create new tables.
					</td>
				</tr>
				<tr>
					<td>Table Relation</td>
					<td>
						A table relation declares a relationship between two tables. This is useful for features like
						<a href="CodeAssistance.html">Code Assistance</a>.
					</td>
				</tr>
			</table>
		</section>
	</body>
</topic>
