<topic>
	<head>
		<title>Query Class</title>
		<toc index="1" />
		<links>
			<link href="Overview.html">Overview</link>
			<link href="..\Language Reference\Queries\Queries.html">SELECT Syntax</link>
		</links>
	</head>
	<body>
		<summary>
			<p>
				The <see cref="T:NQuery.Query">Query</see> class is the most important class in NQuery. This class allows you to execute a
				<a href="Language Reference/Queries/Queries.html">SELECT query</a> against a <a href="DataContext.html">DataContext</a>.
			</p>
		</summary>

		<section title="Syntax">
			<p>
				The syntax is based on SQL-92 (with some extensions from SQL-99) For details see <a href="..\Language Reference\Queries\Queries.html">SELECT Syntax</a>.
			</p>
		</section>

		<section title="Execution Methods">
			<p>
				For your convenience the <see cref="T:NQuery.Query">Query</see> class provides different methods for query execution
				which are summarized in the table below.
			</p>
			<table>
				<tr>
					<th>Method</th>
					<th>Description</th>
				</tr>
				<tr>
					<td>
						<see cref="M:NQuery.Query.ExecuteDataTable">ExecuteDataTable</see>
					</td>
					<td>
						Executes the query and returns the result as <see cref="T:System.Data.DataTable">DataTable</see>.
					</td>
				</tr>
				<tr>
					<td>
						<see cref="M:NQuery.Query.ExecuteScalar">ExecuteScalar</see>
					</td>
					<td>
						Executes the query and returns the first column of the first row.
					</td>
				</tr>
				<tr>
					<td>
						<see cref="M:NQuery.Query.ExecuteSchemaDataTable">ExecuteSchemaDataTable</see>
					</td>
					<td>
						Compiles the query but does not actually execute it. This method retuns an empty  <see cref="T:System.Data.DataTable">DataTable</see>
						in which all column definitions are set as if the query would have been executed.
					</td>
				</tr>
				<tr>
					<td>
						<see cref="M:NQuery.Query.ExecuteDataReader">ExecuteDataReader</see>
					</td>
					<td>
						Executes the query and returns the result as <see cref="T:NQuery.QueryDataReader">QueryDataReader</see>. For query results with large
						amounts of data this method is faster than <see cref="M:NQuery.Query.ExecuteDataTable">ExecuteDataTable</see> because the data is
						not fully loaded in-memory but returned through a light weight, forward-only cursor.
					</td>
				</tr>
				<tr>
					<td>
						<see cref="M:NQuery.Query.ExecuteSchemaReader">ExecuteSchemaReader</see>
					</td>
					<td>
						Compiles the query but does not actually execute it. This method retuns an  <see cref="T:NQuery.QueryDataReader">QueryDataReader</see>
						that will not return any data but has all column definitions set as if the query would have been executed. This method is equivalent to
						<see cref="M:NQuery.Query.ExecuteSchemaDataTable">ExecuteSchemaDataTable</see>.
					</td>
				</tr>
			</table>
		</section>
	</body>
</topic>
